<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Antichrist in flesh unmask'd, the Quakers Christianity vindicated, from the malicious and injurious attempts of [brace] Edward Paye, William Alcott, &amp; Henry Loader, in their late defaming confused book falsly styled, Antichrist in spirit unmask'd, or Quakerism a great delusion, wherein their causeless outrage, folly and falshood are deservedly exposed.</title>
            <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 39 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96383</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1888</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R186514</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">47683537</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 47683537</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172994</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96383)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172994)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2660:26)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Antichrist in flesh unmask'd, the Quakers Christianity vindicated, from the malicious and injurious attempts of [brace] Edward Paye, William Alcott, &amp; Henry Loader, in their late defaming confused book falsly styled, Antichrist in spirit unmask'd, or Quakerism a great delusion, wherein their causeless outrage, folly and falshood are deservedly exposed.</title>
                  <author>Whitehead, George, 1636?-1723.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5-32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Northcott ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed on p. 26: George Whitehead.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Friends' Library (London, England).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Paye, Edw. --  (Edward). --  Antichrist in spirit unmask'd, or, Quakerism a great delusion.</term>
               <term>Antichrist in spirit unmask'd, or, Quakerism a great delusion.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172994:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi rend="blackletterType">Antichriſt in Fleſh <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmask'd,</hi> AND THE <hi>Quakers Chriſtianity Vindicated,</hi> FROM THE Malicious and Injurious Attempts Of
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="blackletterType">Edward Paye,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="blackletterType">William Alcott,</hi> &amp;</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi rend="blackletterType">Henry Loader,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>In their late Defaming Confuſed BOOK Falſly Styled, <hi>Antichriſt in Spirit unmask'd, or Quakeriſm a great Deluſion,</hi> Wherein their Cauſeleſs Outrage, Folly and Falſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood are deſervedly Expoſed.</p>
            <q>But ye are forgers of lies,
<bibl>
                  <hi>Job 13.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi rend="blackletterType">Thomas Northcott,</hi> in <hi>George-yard</hi> in <hi>Lombardſtreet,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:172994:2"/>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172994:2"/>
            <p>CHaritably hoping that many among the People commonly called <hi>Anabaptiſts,</hi> are more Tender and Honeſt minded than ſome of their Miniſters or Leaders, who have ſhewen their Envy and Bitter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs againſt us, I would tenderly propoſe a few things to the more Honeſt, Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and Charitable among them in and about <hi>Deptford</hi> and elſwhere, that may be concerned in reading that Scandalous and Malicious Book againſt us, Falſly ſtiled, <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt in Spirit <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmasked,</hi> or <hi>Quakeriſm a Great Deluſion;</hi> lately Owned and Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed by their Brethren, <hi>Edward Paye, Henry Loader, William Alcott,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">I. That they have Cauſeleſsly and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtly begun a Quarrel againſt us, to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fame us, as a People who have had no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Love and Good-will to them and that People, and maliciouſly tending to Reproach and Blaſt our Credit in what we have ſolemnly profeſſed, as to our Chriſtian Belief and Religion, both to the Civil Government and Nation.</p>
            <p n="2">II. They appear Envious againſt our Preſent Liberty, as Men of a Turbulent,
<pb facs="tcp:172994:3"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:172994:3"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:172994:4"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:172994:4"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:172994:5"/>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172994:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:172994:6"/>Perſecuting Spirit, by ſeeking to invali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date and make void one Condition of our preſent Liberty, which through God's Providence is granted us and them; and that is our Profeſſion of Faith, in <q>the three Divine Witneſſes in Heaven, the Father, Son and Holy Spirit, being one God, bleſſed for evermore:</q> And acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging, <hi>the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament to be given by Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiration.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which Profeſſion, though ſincerely owned and conſented unto by us before the Parliament, and accordingly accepted and inſerted in the Act <hi>For exempting their Majeſties Proteſtant Subjects, diſſenting from the Church of</hi> England, <hi>from the Penalties of certain Laws,</hi> and therein confeſſed to be <hi>a Profeſſion of their Chriſtian Belief:</hi> Yet contrary thereunto theſe Perſons have groſsly Belied and Miſrepreſented <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s,</hi> the People called Quakers; accuſing us with <hi>Vilifying and Contemning the Holy Scriptures,</hi> and that <hi>we own not the Scripture, but ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly allow it,</hi> Epiſt. and Pag. 14. And that <hi>The Quakers are great Enemies to, and Contemners of Holy Scriptures,</hi> p. 20. both contrary to our Sincere and Chriſtian Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, before-cited, and to the Civil Government's Belief and Acceptance thereof; wherein theſe Anabaptiſts have
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172994:6"/>neither done honeſtly towards us, nor prudently towards their Superiors, thus to contradict, and conſequently to affront the Government in its Belief and Charity towards us, and to ſet Subjects at Vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, and to raiſe Perſecution againſt us again, inſtead of being humbly thankful for their and our preſent Liberty.</p>
            <p n="3">III. They have not only abuſed parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Perſons, but a People, a Religious Society, fearing God, and truly eſteem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Holy Scriptures; when we have ſolemnly and ſincerely declared to the Government, <hi>That we believe the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures of the Old and New Teſtament are given by Divine Inſpiration:</hi> Wherein we are Believed, Accepted and Tolerated by the Government. Two or three Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſt Preachers divulge the contrary to the World in Print, <hi>That the Quakers are great Enemies to, and Contemners of Holy Scriptures, and no Chriſtians, but deluded Impoſtors, and their Profeſſion a Compound of Hereſies,</hi> p. 8, 20. And what's the Conſequence, but therefore the Quakers are not fit to be tolerated, nor to have their Liberty of Conſcience or Exerciſe of Religion? And no Doubt, had theſe angry Anabaptiſts Power, we ſhould not enjoy our Liberties, the very Nature and Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of theſe their Bitter Lying Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctives,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172994:7"/>being to bring Perſecution upon us, as a People not to be given any Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit unto, in our ſolemn Profeſſion before Authority.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. Pray obſerve, That much of the ſaid Pamphlet, or Book againſt us, ſtyled, <hi>Antichriſt in Spirit,</hi> is collected out of other Books and Pamphlets of our Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, long ſince Anſwered and Refuted; and their Authorities are utterly denied by us. As the <hi>Weſtmorland Petitioners,</hi> who were Envious Perſecutors, <hi>Thomas Hicks</hi> his Fictitious Abuſive <hi>Dialogues,</hi> who was proved a notorious Forger of Lies: And a moſt Malicious Libel, ſtyled, <hi>Tyranny and Hypocriſy,</hi> &amp;c. without Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor's Name, yet cited and inſiſted upon againſt us. Thus Credulous and Malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous are theſe Perſons, <hi>Edward Paye, Henry Loader, William Alcott,</hi> as to take Scandal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Pamphlets on Truſt, whoſe Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities we utterly Deny, and Challenge them to prove them Authentick; they having been long ſince ſufficiently An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, Diſproved and Refuted, in our Friends Books; one entituled, <hi>The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Quaker,</hi> in Folio; another, <hi>Reaſon againſt Railing;</hi> another, <hi>The Counterfeit Chriſtian,</hi> in 8<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. another, <hi>Judas and the Jews;</hi> another, <hi>The Divinity of Chriſt,</hi> &amp;c. in 4<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. another, <hi>The Chriſtianity of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172994:7"/>called Quakers vindicated,</hi> in Anſwer to Dr. <hi>Forde;</hi> and many others of our Friends Books, which contain ſufficient Anſwer to all the chief Objections and Reproaches ſcraped up in this Inveterate Lying Pamphlet aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="5">V. They have Unjuſtly and Falſly Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talized and Perverted divers of our Friends Words and Paſſages in their Books, leaving out the Explanatory Words and Sentences.</p>
            <p n="6">VI. They have argued fallaciouſly in divers things, deducing Inferences and Charges from a particular to a general, as from a particular Perſon, chargeable (as ſuppoſed) they charge the General, that is, a Body of People, which is very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt; as if where we find falſe Logick, Abſurdities and Errors committed, by theſe particular Perſons, <hi>Edward Paye, Henry Loader, William Alcott,</hi> we ſhould charge them upon their whole Society or Body, ſurely they would not be ſo ſerv'd.</p>
            <p n="7">VII. It would be well for their Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, who are more Peaceable and Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, not to be ſubject to ſuch Envious and Turbulent Teachers; whoſe Work tends to Sedition, Strife and Diſcord, among their Neighbours; but rather to reprehend their Rage and Railery, and caution them to live peaceably among
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172994:8"/>their peaceable Neighbours, that mean them no harm.</p>
            <p n="8">VIII. It is a manifeſt Sign the Lord has forſaken their Shadows and Forms of Profeſſion, who are turned into ſo much Envy and Bitterneſs as theſe Men are, againſt other Diſſenters more Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian like than themſelves: That they are turned from the Spirit into the Fleſh, which Envy is a fruit of. The Primitive Tenderneſs, Simplicity and Spiritual Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries and Preaching that were former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly among ſome of their Ancient and Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Brethren being now loſt, and ſlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by theſe Gain-ſaying Adverſaries, (which is their ſad Apoſtacy) who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of owning the Sufficiency of the Spirit's Teaching, as they did formerly, now oppoſe <hi>Immediate Inſpiration,</hi> p. 16. <hi>and poſſeſſing the Kingdom of Christ,</hi> p. 52. and ſay that, <hi>The Diſciples did not expect this Christ to come into them,</hi> p. 53. (who is the ſame only and very Chriſt of God, of whom the Holy Scriptures teſtifie) they Quoting <hi>Deut.</hi> 18.15. <hi>Acts</hi> 3.22. <hi>Mat.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Luk.</hi> 24.39. <hi>Joh.</hi> 20.19. p. 52, 53. And alſo deriding at the Quakers exhorting People to <hi>Turn to the Light within,</hi> p. 54, 55, 56. Thus Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, Blind and Dark, have theſe Baptiſt Preachers ſhewn themſelves, and how
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172994:8"/>groſly Ignorant of the Spiritual Appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Kingdom of Chriſt and his Light within, and his own and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Teſtimony thereof. The Lord de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver well-meaning People from ſuch blind Guides.</p>
            <p>Of the Word <hi>Quakeriſm</hi> (which is a Nick-name in Deriſion put upon our Chriſtian Profeſſion) you tell us, <hi>It's de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived from a Gesture uſed <hi>Much</hi> among them formerly in their Meetings;</hi> (meaning the Meetings of the People called Quakers) <hi>as was manifest</hi> (ſay you) <hi>by the</hi> Weſtmorland <hi>Petitioners,</hi> viz. <hi>That their Practice did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly ſavour of Sorcery, becauſe of the <hi>Swellings, Quakings, Roatings and Foamings,</hi> that were among them at their Meetings,</hi> p. 7, 8.</p>
            <p>Were you Eye or Ear-Witneſſes of theſe Geſtures? No, you had this Story from the <hi>Westmorland</hi> Petitioners; and what were they but a Company of envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous perſecuting Prieſts, and Magiſtrates whom they had Inſtigated to Perſecution? Are you not ſo Credulous as to take upon Truſt any old Story to render the People called Quakers Odious and Ridiculous? Is this your Chriſtianity and Religion? Lord deliver every well-meaning Perſon from you and your Envy. We deny your Story of <hi>Swellings</hi> and <hi>Foamings,</hi> as
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172994:9"/>charged <hi>on <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>s</hi> or our Meetings in <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morland,</hi> &amp;c. But that there has been Weeping, Trembling and Lamentation, ſometimes in our Solemn and Religious Aſſemblies in <hi>Westmorland</hi> and other Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, I and many more were and are Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; when the glorious Power and Day of the Lord aroſe and broke forth in our Meetings, to the Breaking, Humbling and Tendering many Hearts, from a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Senſe of his Divine and Dreadful Preſence, which was truly felt among us; and that the Holy Men of God did Witneſs <hi>Quaking</hi> and <hi>Trembling,</hi> as Holy Scripture teſtifies: This you grant is true. <hi>And the ſame</hi> (ſay you) <hi>may be ſaid of Wicked Men and Devils.</hi> And what then? God's dreadful Power and Preſence can make all Dread and Tremble and Bow before it, even both good Men and bad Men, yea and Devils alſo; yet the Power is the ſame that's over all. Wicked Men and Devils have been ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times terrified by it, and made to tremble for fear of his Wrath, becauſe of their guilt of Iniquity; and good Men and Women have in an humble and a contrite Heart and Spirit, Trembled in a Holy Reverence and Senſe of the Preſence and Power of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt among them, in their Inward Attention upon
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172994:9"/>him and his Word, and in their fervent Prayers and Supplications to God. And how can it be better than Blaſphemy to account this <hi>Sorcery?</hi> Such wicked Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and Inſinuation we utterly deny and teſtifie againſt, and put you to prove it who have received this falſe Story againſt us, of <hi>Swellings and Foamings, and Sorcery,</hi> &amp;c. at our Meetings, with ſuch wicked defaming Conſtructions. I my ſelf was frequent at our Meetings in <hi>West<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morland</hi> very early, near the very begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of them in that Country, and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly Declare it, I never ſaw ſuch Geſtures, as <hi>Swellings</hi> and <hi>Foamings:</hi> And I have lately enquired of ſeveral of our Ancient Friends who were converſant at thoſe early Meetings in the North, and they Declare the ſame, That they never ſaw ſuch Poſtures in our Friend's Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings. But ſet caſe any have been diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered through ſome Natural Infirmity Diſtemper, Swooning or Falling Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs—</p>
            <p>—What does this affect us or our Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings on a Religious Account? It may be ſome of your own People's Caſe. And ſuppoſe it ſhould be made appear that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Anabaptiſts, after they have been Dipt and receiv'd into Church-Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, have run Mad or Diſtracted; and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172994:10"/>others guilty of great Enormities; how would this affect either their Church-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion or Society? Pray conſider it, have you done well, or as you would be done by, in raking up and aggravating old Stories againſt the People called Quakers, to render them as black and deformed as you can? Upon this Story you make this farther Aggravation, from <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.39. <hi>We reed of him that was Poſſeſſed, that he Foamed when the Diabolical Spirit did tear him.</hi> True, and what then? Is this any Proof againſt the Quakers, that they are ſo Poſſeſſed or guilty of Sorcery? No ſure.—</p>
            <p>—We read further alſo concerning that Man that was poſſeſſed, <hi>That when he was brought unto Jeſus, as ſoon as the Spirit ſaw him, he tore him, and fell down on the ground wallowing and foaming; and that when Jeſus rebuked the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nclean Spirit, and charged him to come out of him, and enter no more into him; then the Spirit cryed and rent him ſore, and came out,</hi> Mark 9.20, 25, 26. Luke 9.39, 42, 43. Now, ſuppoſe, that in any meeting of the People called Quakers, any ſuch Operations or Geſture has been in any particular Perſon formerly, that ſome Unclean Spirit has ſo torn and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered him or her; we may charitably believe it has been becauſe Jeſus Chriſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172994:10"/>has come in Spirit and Power among them, to rebuke and caſt out ſuch Unclean Spirits, and to deliver them that were infeſted thereby; When our Friends have been ſolemnly met together in his Name and Fear, in Faſting and Prayer, to wait upon and worſhip him. And that ſuch Unclean Spirit did not enter them in ſuch Aſſemblies as ours, but when they were Followers of the Envious Perſecut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Prieſts (who uſed to Revile and Rail againſt the Quakers in their Pulpits) and of ſuch Malicious Preachers as theſe Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, who, as perſons poſſeſſed with a Lying, Unclean Spirit, are now ſtill foaming out their own Shame and Malice againſt an Innocent People, as theſe Men have done in their Lying Abuſive Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlet, falſly pretending to Unmask Antichriſt in Spirit, whilſt their Work of Malice and Falſhood beſpeaks Antichriſt, in their proud puft up envious Fleſh and Fleſhly Minds, ſcurrilouſly perverting our Words, detracting and defaming others more Harmleſs than themſelves, and no whit inferior to them, as Men, in Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Parts or Morals. And I hope we are and ſhall be of more Credit and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in what we ſolemnly declare and write, than they in falſly telling the World, <hi>That 'tis nothing ſo believed by us,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:172994:11"/>as pretended in our Pamphlet,</hi> meaning that Paper concerning our Chriſtianity; which they not being able to refute, now falſly tell People, <hi>That 'tis nothing ſo believed by us;</hi> as <hi>Henry Loader</hi> and <hi>William Alcott,</hi> have unjuſtly done in their Epiſtle to the Reader; though they are ſo credulous of their Brother <hi>Edward Paye</hi>'s Work or Pamphlet, as to <hi>Believe neither Ambition, Self-Interest or Prejudice moved him to it; but purely the Honour of God, Defence of Truth, and Good of Souls:</hi> And they alſo <hi>Hope and Believe that he hath been careful truly to cite the Quakers own Authors.</hi> But we know the contrary, and that he hath both falſly cited, groſly belyed, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted the Quaker's Words and Authors, and taken many falſe Things on Credit, and in their Implicit Faith; not only the ſaid Story from the <hi>Westmorland Petition<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> but alſo out of his Brother <hi>Thomas Hicks,</hi> his abominable Forgeries and Lies in his fictions <hi>Dialogues,</hi> and others, long ſince refuted, to his own and his Compurgators and Abetters utter Shame and Diſgrace. And you who are ſuch credulous Approvers and Eſpouſers of this <hi>Edward Paye</hi>'s malicious Work againſt us, do charge us with this horrid Lye, <hi>viz. That the Holy Scriptures, this Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of Men contemn and vilifie.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:172994:11"/>
            <p>God knows the contrary, and he will judge righteouſly between us. You have herein Groſsly Belyed and Defamed us, our real Intention, and our Solemn Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion for the Holy Scriptures, and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere Eſteem of them, as therein we have been Credited by the Government, and many others, we doubt not but we ſhall ſtill have Credit againſt your ſhameful Lyes and Defamations to the contrary; whereby you have moſt Diabolically and Foully Foamed out your <hi>own</hi> Shame and Envy, as will farther appear, That the Foaming Unclean Spirit, and Lying Devil is not caſt out of you. Oh! how well it would be for you, if you would humbly wait for and own Chriſt's Appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in Spirit, and Power to caſt out that Unclean, Lying Spirit that Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſes you, and has moved you to approve and divulge ſo many groſs Lyes as are in your ſaid Book.</p>
            <p>Out of your Brother, <hi>Thomas Hick</hi>'s <hi>Dialogue,</hi> you repreſent the Quaker to anſwer thus, <hi>viz. When we make uſe of the Scripture, it is</hi> only <hi>to quiet and ſtop their Clamours that plead for it as their Rule,</hi> p. 14.</p>
            <p>This is one of your Brother <hi>Hick</hi>'s groſs Forgeries in the Quaker's Name, which you have taken on Truſt out of his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172994:12"/>fictitious Dialogue. Oh! bluſh and be aſhamed of adopting and promoting ſuch Falſe, Deceitful Stuff; and alſo of your ſubjoyning in the Perſon of the Quakers this Forgery, <hi>viz.</hi> 
               <q>We own not the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture; we ſeemingly allow it, but our End in this is only to ſtop their Cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours that plead for it as their Rule.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Words, ſubjoyned to <hi>Hick</hi>'s Forgeries, I charge upon you <hi>Edward Paye, William Alcott</hi> and <hi>Henry Loader,</hi> as abominably Falſe and Slanderous. Will this Deceitful Method bring any Honour to you, or honeſt Proſelytes to your Church, think ye? Would you be Popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and Famous by ſuch groſs Forgery? Is this the Fruit of your Religion, you Dip and Proſelyte People into? You are hard put to it: It is a Sign your Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation is decreaſing, and your Glory eclips'd, when you can eſpouſe and invent ſuch groſs Forgeries, and make Lyes your Refuge. Wo unto you Lying Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites; When and where did ever we, the People called Quakers, ſay, as you ſay in our Name? <hi>viz. That we own not the Scripture; we ſeemingly allow it, but our End in this is only to stop their Clamours,</hi> &amp;c. Theſe your horrid abuſive Forgeries will be a ſore Blot and heavy Burthen upon you.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:172994:12"/>
            <p>And now, pray, obſerve what ſtrange Teſt or Proof, your Agent, <hi>Edward Paye,</hi> puts upon us to evince Immediate Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>viz. Now let the Quakers reſolve me by their Immediate Inſpirations, What thoſe Things were that Jeſus did, that are not writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,</hi> John 21.25. <hi>And what were the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of that Writing on the Ground,</hi> John 8.6, 8. <hi>or elſe let their proud Boaſtings of Immediate Inſpiration be condemned to perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Silence, and Shame cover their Faces. And waiting for their Reſolve herein,</hi> &amp;c.— p. 15, 16.</p>
            <p>And why ſo? If we do not reſolve by Immediate Inſpiration what thoſe things were that Jeſus did, that are not written, <hi>John</hi> 21.25. And what were the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents of that Writing on the Ground, <hi>John</hi> 8.6, 8. Hereupon you have paſt Unjuſt Judgment, and falſly charged us with proud Boaſting, and argued abſurdly againſt <hi>Immediate Inſpiration,</hi> as if none have the Spirit of Chriſt unleſs they know and can declare all things it knows; or could write as many Books of thoſe Things Chriſt did, as (was ſuppoſed) the World it ſelf could not contain, <hi>John</hi> 21.25. And then, by this, you Baptiſts will greatly fall ſhort of being Chriſt's Miniſters or Embaſſadors, and have ſhut your ſelves out from any Share in the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:172994:13"/>Spirit of Chriſt, or Divine Inſpiration. And how then will you prove your Call to Baptize People in Water? Though herein you have moſt egregiouſly contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted your ſelves, in pretending to <hi>Chriſt in you,</hi> from 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. and to be the Temples of God, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. <hi>To be in Chriſt new Creatures,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. p. 22. <hi>And to have the Spirit of Chriſt, or elſe none of his,</hi> p 23. And that <hi>Chriſt gives his Spirit to them that obey him,</hi> Acts 5.32. p. 69. But does he give the Knowledg of all thoſe other things that he did (which are not written) to all them that obey him, think ye? Or otherwiſe is it juſt to condemn them all to perpetual Silence and Shame, for owning that Chriſt has given them his Spirit, when they cannot tell all thoſe other things? Muſt we needs be as omniſcient as the Spirit of God is, or elſe be condemned as wholly deſtitute thereof? Do you think you have well argued, or given juſt Judgment in this Matter? Oh! Blind Guides, ſelf-contradicting and ſelf-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned Hypocrites. How hath Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt appeared in your Proud and Envi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Fleſh againſt <hi>Chriſt in Spirit?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On <hi>Matthew</hi> 24.26. you ſay, <hi>It is more than probable, That Chriſt pointed at this Generation of Impoſtors, the Quakers; who ſay, Behold he is in the Secret Chambers,</hi> [which is a groſs Lye, by the way] <hi>ay
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:172994:13"/>
                  <hi>within</hi> thee, not at a diſtance from thee,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>To deem them Impoſtors that ſay Chriſt is within thee or them, is to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Holy Apoſtles Impoſtors, who preached <hi>Christ within the Word, nigh in thy Heart,</hi> Rom. 10.6, 7, 8. (which therefore was not ſeparate from them, and only at a Diſtance) yea and to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der your ſelves alſo Impoſtors, who have confeſſed the ſame Truth of <hi>Chriſt within,</hi> p. 22, 23, 69. from 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.22. <hi>John</hi> 16.7. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.32. Thus you Anabaptiſt Preachers have contradicted your ſelves, as well as ſhewn your Antichriſtian Spirit againſt <hi>Chriſt within;</hi> and that you are blind Guides, and ſelf-contradictory Oppoſers of the Myſtery of Chriſt, as well as Defamers of us for his ſake.</p>
            <p>You moſt ſhamefully belie the People called Quakers in your Compariſon, p. 18. where you ſay, <hi>The Names they (i. e.</hi> the Quakers) <hi>give the Holy Scriptures,</hi> viz. <hi>no better than an Old Almanack, Precepts and Traditions of Men,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Pray where do they (that is, the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called Quakers) give the Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures thoſe Names you charge upon them? They are ſuch groſs, notorious, old Lyes, that it is high Time for you to be hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribly aſhamed thereof, as they are quite out of date with all ſober minded People
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172994:14"/>that know us; ſo we doubt not but you, who are now the Promoters thereof, will be as much out of Credit as the firſt Fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menters, have long been.</p>
            <p>You abuſe and wrong us about the <hi>Titles</hi> of our Books <hi>(as if higher than we give to the Holy Scriptures)</hi> perverting them by leaving out the Explanatory part of the Titles; as for inſtance <hi>[A true and Everlaſting Rule]</hi> being the firſt Words of the Title, you leave out the next fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing in the ſame Sentence, <hi>viz. [from God diſcovered]</hi> thus you deal very diſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly by them and others. p. 18, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We know none among us that call <hi>the Holy Scriptures, a Dead or Carnal Letter,</hi> nor do we own the Words. By the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi> we intend the <hi>Holy Teſtimonies and Doctrin of Faith and Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice</hi> therein contained, which is both Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Spiritual to them that are alive unto God in Chriſt. Though the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Letter or Writing in it ſelf alone be Dead, the Holy Matter contained in it is Living, to them that are Living and Spiritual. There is the <hi>Letter</hi> of the Shadows of the Law and Old Covenant, which is aboliſhed by Chriſt, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Dead. And all Shadows and Carnal Ordinances, comparatively, are but <hi>dead Letter.</hi> When <hi>Paul</hi> preferred the <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172994:14"/>of the Spirit to the Oldneſs of the Letter,</hi> and the <hi>Miniſtry of the Spirit</hi> above the <hi>Letter;</hi> this was not to ſlight or contemn the Holy Scriptures: No more do we in allowing the Holy Spirit, the ſame Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference which the Scripture allows. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over to them that are Dead to the Spirit, to God and Chriſt, the Scripture is Dead, the Words therein are Dead, and even the Spiritual Living Miniſtry is Dead as to them; <hi>The Savour of Death unto Death, in them that Periſh; but the Savour of Life unto Life in them that are Saved.</hi> As the meer Characters or Letters, as written in Paper and Ink, have no Sound nor Voyce till Sound be given them by the Reader; <hi>ſo,</hi> the Words contained in them, or Preaching from them, have no Life, but as the <hi>Spirit</hi> gives it, without which all Preaching is Dead and Fruitleſs. I am perſuaded in Conſcience, That in theſe things our Friends real Intentions in their Writings is explained (and never to contemn the <hi>Holy Scriptures</hi>) and our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries hard and ill Conſtructions an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered. And though the Holy Spirit, from whence the Holy Scriptures pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded be of itſelf <hi>All ſufficient</hi> to guide in <hi>all the Ways of God</hi> both <hi>with</hi> and <hi>without</hi> the Scriptures (or where they are not in Writing) this is not to contemn or
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172994:15"/>ſlight them where they are; but to uſe them with the help of the ſame Spirit, rightly to underſtand and practiſe them: It being the <hi>Inspiration of the Almighty that giveth <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderstanding</hi> of the Mind and Will of God, and without which the Scriptures cannot be truly underſtood. It was from the ſame Inſpiration (or Spirit of God) the Holy Scriptures firſt came; and from thence they had their Authority and real Credit. And by no other Argument or Demonſtration can the Divine Authority of Holy Scriptures be effectually proved or evinced, to ſuch as queſtion their Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, but by the ſame Holy Spirit of God in Man, bearing Witneſs to the Truths therein contained. It muſt be ſomething ſuperior to the Scriptures, that muſt ſo prove their Divine Authority to them that queſtion the ſame, which we do not at all, bleſſed be God; and therefore Challenge theſe Adverſaries <hi>E. Paye</hi> and <hi>W. Alcott</hi> to prove, that the People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> or any Perſons continuing in So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety with them, do ſay, <hi>The Holy Scripture is but a dead carnal Letter,</hi> or that ſo call the <hi>Doctrins or Teſtimonies therein contained;</hi> for we poſitively deny any ſuch Expreſſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Note</hi> alſo, that theſe Adverſaries have apparently perverted and wronged <hi>George Whitehead</hi>'s Words, both in Citation and
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172994:15"/>Conſtruction, about the Holy Scriptures and the Perſon of Chriſt, <hi>p.</hi> 11, 12. and 22. And likewiſe groſly Abuſed, Wrong'd and Miſcharged <hi>G. Fox, James Parnell, G. Keith,</hi> foully perverting and miſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruing their Words, <hi>p.</hi> 28, 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 59. And they have alſo Abuſed, Vilified, Defamed and Wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>W. Smith, H. Smith, J. Naylor, E. Burroughs, Iſaac Pennington, S. Crisp, W. P.</hi> and others, Men of better Fame and Repute than themſelves, and more Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Innocent than their Defamers.</p>
            <p>Now I would ſeriouſly enquire of you <hi>William Alcott</hi> and <hi>Henry Loader,</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Was <hi>Edward Paye</hi> deputed and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by your Congregation, or any ſelect Aſſembly of Elders or Miniſters of the Baptized People or Churches, to Write and Publiſh his ſaid Book againſt the People called Quakers? Or did he do it on his own Authority and Head, with your Approbation only?</p>
            <p n="2">2. What Miniſters or Elders of your Churches, beſides your ſelves, did peruſe and approve of <hi>Edward Paye</hi>'s ſaid Book before Printed, and of the Printing thereof, to defame us as a People?</p>
            <p n="3">3. Is the ſaid <hi>Edward Paye</hi> indeed eſteemed among you and your Society a good Chriſtian, a Perſon of a Godly and Sober Converſation, of ſound Judgment
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172994:16"/>Piety and Parts, meet to manage Matters of Controverſie about Religion?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Do you intend to ſtand by him the ſaid <hi>Edward Paye,</hi> in all the Matters that he has Written in Charge, both againſt certain Perſons and againſt the People called Quakers, in his Book?</p>
            <p>Pray give us your direct and plain An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to theſe Queſtions; the Reaſon whereof being, 1. That <hi>Edward Paye</hi> and you alſo have concerned us as a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, in your ſevere and unjuſt Accuſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, in his and your Book. 2. That we have an Anſwer drawn up more Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſive and Particular, reſerved for Publication, if we may find a farther Occaſion or Neceſſity for it. Therefore 'tis but equal and reaſonable you ſhould be ſo Ingenuous, as to tell us plainly, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your ſaid Book with our Anſwer may affect your ſelves only, or your whole Society of People; ſeeing it affects us as a whole Society of People. If your Book againſt us, be only your own private Act whoſe Names are to it, and not more generally owned, nor ſtood by among your People; we would be ſo juſt as not to reflect it on your whole Society or People.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>London, <date>
                     <hi>the 2d of the 1ſt Mo.</hi> 1691/2.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>By a Lover of Peace, and the Souls of Men,</hi> 
                  <hi rend="blackletterType">George Whitehead.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <pb n="27" facs="tcp:172994:16"/>
            <p>TO conclude in general againſt your falſe Charges, and manifold Abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and Calumnies, contained in your ſaid Book, <hi>i. e. Antichriſt in Spirit,</hi> &amp; to anticipate farther Objections on the Matters herein.</p>
            <p>We ſincerely Profeſs and Declare in the Sight of God and Men, that we do faithfully Believe and Profeſs, That the Holy Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament were given by <hi>Divine In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiration:</hi> And that the three <hi>Divine Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes</hi> in Heaven above, namely, the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Son and Holy Ghoſt, are one True and Eternal God, Bleſſed for evermore, whoſe Omnipreſence and Omnipotency, we alſo Believe and Profeſs.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>Divinity</hi> and <hi>Humanity</hi> or Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood of our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, the Eternal Word of God: And that in the fulneſs of time he took Fleſh, being Miraculouſly Conceived by the Holy Ghoſt and Born of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and ſuffered the cruel Death of the Croſs, as an Univerſal Offering and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice both in his Body and Blood ſhed thereon, for the Sins of the whole World, and was Buried, and Roſe again the third Day, and <hi>Viſibly</hi> Aſcended (was ſeen in his Aſcending) and paſſed into Heaven and Glory: And that he Aſcended far
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172994:17"/>above all Heavens, that he might fill all Things: And that by his Suffering and Sacrifice he hath obtained Eternal Redem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption for us, which through Faith in his Name and Power, true Repentance and Converſion, we livingly receive and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually partake of.</p>
            <p>That we are not Pardoned, Juſtified, Redeemed or Saved by our own Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, Works, Merits or Deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings; but by the Righteouſneſs, Merits and Works, of this our Bleſſed Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, being both impart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and imputed to us, as he is of God made unto us Wiſdom, Righteouſneſs, Sanctification and Redemption. Our Reconciliation, Redemption, Pardon, Sanctification and Juſtification, having reſpect both to his ſuffering Death and Blood upon the Croſs: (As the one Peace - Offering and Sacrifice, and as our High Prieſt, thereby making At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonement and Reconciliation for us, and giving himſelf a Ranſom for all Mankind.) And alſo to the effectual ſaving Work of his Grace and good Spirit within us, bringing us to experience true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, Regeneration and the new Birth, wherein we partake of the Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Chriſt's Sufferings and Power of his Reſurrection.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:172994:17"/>
            <p>In which Grace we ought to perſevere in newneſs of Life and faithful Obedience unto him, unto the end that we may be Heirs of the Eternal Salvation, which Chriſt is the Author of.—We ſincerely Believe alſo, That the <hi>Man Chriſt Jeſus</hi> is the only Mediator between God and Men, our Interceſſor and Advocate with the Father; and that he exerciſeth his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Office, and his Prieſtly and Propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Office in his Kingdom and Church here on Earth, wherein he Governs, and plentifully affords both Immediate Inſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration and Inſtruction to his Faithful Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, who walk in his Light to guide them into all Truth; and he that hath not the Spirit of Chriſt is none of his.—And that this ſame Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who dyed for all Men, enlightens every Man coming into the World, and was and is the Light of the World, the Way, the Truth and the Life; and that the ſame Chriſt that was Crucified and put to Death, as concerning the Fleſh, and quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by the Spirit and Power of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he is Inwardly Revealed and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually in the Hearts of True and Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Believers, by his Holy Spirit, Life, Light and Grace: And that therefore his coming and appearing Outwardly <hi>in the Fleſh</hi> and <hi>Inwardly in the Spirit,</hi> cannot
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172994:18"/>render him two Chriſts, but one and the ſame very Chriſt of God bleſſed for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſaving Baptiſm, which is, that of the Spirit and the Lord's Supper in his Church and Kingdom, we believe and receive in him the Subſtance Spiritually, not apprehending our ſelves bound to remain under any outward Shadow or Type thereof in the clear Goſpel-day of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The Immortality of the <hi>Soul</hi> of Man, being Created in God's own Image, and Inſpired by him that formed Man. And the <hi>Reſurrection of <hi>the Dead</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Eternal Judgment:</hi> And that every Man ſhall be reſerved in his own diſtinct Being for his due and future Reward; the Wicked un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Day of Judgment, Deſtruction and Wrath; but the Righteous unto Eternal Life and Glory, in their Spiritual Bodies like unto Chriſt's Glorious Body, where they ſhall be equal to the Angels of God in Heaven. Theſe Things we ſincerely Believe and Profeſs according to Holy Scripture-Teſtimony, and as ſet forth therein, as the Lord is pleaſed to give us Underſtanding thereof.—Being ready and willing to give more large Account and Demonſtration of our Holy and Chriſtian Profeſſion, as the Lord ſhall lay
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172994:18"/>a neceſſity upon us. And our Belief and Profeſſion of theſe Matters is not new to us, but according to that Light and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding we have received of the Lord and believed from the Beginning, ſince we were a Suffering People gathered by him; as alſo divers of our Ancient Friend's Miniſtry, Books and Writings, do more fully ſignifie and demonſtrate.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>To evince with what Conſciences theſe Anabaptiſts, <hi>E. Paye, W. Alcott</hi> and <hi>H. L.</hi> have writ againſt the Quakers, pray ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve theſe two or three Inſtances more.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>E. P.</hi> &amp;c. p. 46. <hi>read p.</hi> 6, 7. Saul's <hi>Errand to</hi> Damaſcus. <hi>And</hi> G. Fox <hi>takes the Name to himſelf, ſaying, He is the Eternal Judge of Quick and Dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is notoriouſly falſe in Fact, being in the very ſame Book <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rand,</hi> recorded among thoſe Matters <hi>Fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly</hi> charged on <hi>G. F.</hi> by his Adverſaries the Prieſts and others, in the <hi>County of</hi> Lanca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, in their Petition, <hi>p.</hi> 1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6. of <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Errand,</hi> where <hi>G. F.</hi> oppoſeth and anſwereth their Objections.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>E. P.</hi> &amp;c. p. 29. <hi>That they</hi> (meaning the Quakers) <hi>ſay, That Christ hath no Body but his Church.</hi> Quoting <hi>Saul</hi>'s <hi>Errand, p.</hi> 9.</p>
            <pb n="32" facs="tcp:172994:19"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Which is notoriouſly falſe again. For it was the ſaid Prieſt's Objection a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>L. F. that he profeſſed, That Christ had never any Body but his Church,</hi> Saul<hi>'s</hi> Errand, p. 2. Which was alſo falſe, and there recorded among their other falſe Charges objected; tho' in the Anſwer it is confeſſed, <hi>That Chriſt's Church is his Body:</hi> 'Tis alſo confeſſed, <hi>That we are Members of his Body, of his Fleſh, and of his Bones:</hi> Which grants his <hi>particular Body,</hi> and his Churches Union therewith. Therefore, far from ſuch Profeſſion, as, <hi>That Chriſt had never any Body but his Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>E. P.</hi> &amp;c. p. 59. <hi>See</hi> Parnell<hi>'s Shield of Truth,</hi> p. 12. <hi>Where he calls Water-Baptiſm a formal Invention and Imitation of Men, and ſo a meer Deluſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This <hi>James Parnell</hi> ſpeaks not of <hi>Water-Baptiſm,</hi> without Diſtinction, as they ſtate it againſt him for he ſaith it was <hi>a Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure,</hi> (meaning as <hi>John</hi> and the Diſciples uſed it) but of <hi>Sprinkling Infants,</hi> as he ſaith, <hi>He received Water upon his Face, as his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents told him.</hi> This he calls an <hi>Invention of Men</hi> (and ſo do Baptiſts, I think) <hi>p.</hi> 67, 68. <hi>Collection of</hi> J. P.<hi>'s VVritings.</hi> Thus Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morral and Unjuſt are theſe Anabaptiſts in writing againſt us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:172994:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
